Guide to the Gay Cable Network Archives, 1982-2001 MSS.231
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series XI: Gay USA
  - 1992 Vol. X
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 33 [Air date: 8/13/1992], August 1992; ID: 231.0365 (Box 23, Media ID: 231.0365)
      7. GCN Sports: The Olympics are covered. Magic Johnson leads to an increase in HIV testing. The New York Physique Team is covered.
      8. Naming Names: Nightline covers the dismissal of Franz Tyler, who states he was let go from the Bush campaign because he was gay. Viewers are encouraged to write to Tom Bettag, executive producer.
      9. Lavender Health: Robert Penn, assistant director of education at Gay Men's Health Crisis.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 35 [Air date: 8/27/1992], August 1992; ID: 231.0366 (Box 23, Media ID: 231.0366)
      1. News Notes: The New York Times provides continual coverage of the Republicans avoiding gay issues.
      2. The GCN team, including Lou Maletta are in Houston for the Republican National Convention. Maletta and the team cover the Republicans support of abstinence-only education and criminal prosecution for 'anyone who knowingly[…]transmit[s] the AIDS virus.' Republican party statements on AIDS prevention are displayed on-screen, including 'We reject the notion that the distribution of clean needles and condoms are the solution to stopping the spread of AIDS.', and stresses 'marital fidelity, abstinence, and a drug-free lifestyle.' The statement also lauds the Boy Scouts of America for 'defending decency' and calls for the disbanding of the Corporation for Public Broadcasting. The final statement: "Unlike the Democratic party and its candidate, we support the continued exclusion of homosexuals from the military as a matter of good order and discipline."
      3. ACT UP protests outside the Astrodome. 12 activists were injured, 3 hospitalized, and 6 arrested. Footage is shown of police roughing up protesters. A press conference held by ACT UP after the protest is shown. An ACT UP protester reads a statement that the Houston police did not issue a dispersal warning and instead came charging into the crowd. A protester named B.C. Craig was struck with a baton after 'not leaving quickly enough.' A protester who was beaten by police (and has a bandage around his forehead) speaks about the protest. Another ACT UP protester shows his bruised and bloodied arm and back. Another protester talks about being beaten and trampled by horses. Another protester speaks about being beaten while officers shouted, "Run faggot run!"
      COMMERCIAL: Mixed Blood, a play
      4. Mother's Voices pleads with the Bush administration to support The Ryan White Emergency Care Act. Lili Rundback, Dorothy Faegins, and Rae Ceil Marsh speak.
      COMMERCIAL: Naya Natural Spring Water
      5. Robert Dornan is interviewed about gays in the military, specifically Margarethe Cammermeyer. He states that Cammermeyer's family "would rather have had a mom who wasn't a lesbian." When asked if he's talked to Cammermeyer's children, Dornan states "I've seen them interviewed. It tore that family apart as it always does." Dornan states that gay men in the military would do nothing but have sex with each other and destroy morale. Dornan states that monogamous gay relationships don't exist. Elanor Van Middlesworth, a delegate, is interviewed and states that gays and lesbians should not have equal rights and should instead 'control themselves'. "I don't like to say gay, I like to say homosexual." Van Middlesworth also makes bizarre statements about the Cracker Barrel controversy that gays should not 'handle food' because customers might get AIDS. Michael Undseth, a delegate, is asked what he would do if his son came out to him: "He wouldn't. Because he's not." Undseth states that people choose to be gay and that all people are born heterosexual, and that gays 'recruit'. He recommends counseling and psychotherapy to 'cure' gays. A group of young Republicans happily chant "Burn the log cabin!" A young Republican states "We do not include special rights." Frank Ricchiazzi, a log cabin delegate is interviewed.
      6. Lee Sharmat relates that security was constantly trailing GCN and made one arrest. Mary Fisher gives a speech about compassion and tolerance in relation to AIDS. Lou Maletta narrates that after Fisher's speech, Steve Bradley, a GCN reporter and Fisher's friend, was questioned for the fourth time by security because of a t-shirt he wore stating 'No-one Knows I'm HIV-Positive'. Footage is then shown of security harassing Lou Maletta and Bradley. Maletta is led away by security, and a GCN employee is handcuffed and led away. Maletta states Beth Levo, the employee led away in handcuffs, was charged with assaulting a police officer and detained for nine hours. Maletta then states the ACLU is taking on the case.
      7. Report From the Capitol: Abortion rights activists plan several protests in front of the White House. Venus Thrash, an activist, announces she will be arrested tomorrow at the protest, and is interviewed about being an African-American activist.
      8. The play Mixed Blood is covered, which posits that the AIDS virus was intentionally created. Aubrey Hampton, the writer is interviewed.
      9. Lavender Health: Interview with Joe Franco of VOCAL.
      COMMERCIAL: Naya Natural Spring Water (new commercial featuring male bodybuilder)
      10. Naming Names: News articles use terms like 'gay agenda', 'homosexual lifestyle', 'innocent victims of AIDS', and 'family values', which GLAAD is trying to discourage.
      11. Lee Sharmat talks about how frightening it was to watch the RNC over the credits.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 37 [Air date: 9/10/1992], September 1992; ID: 231.0367 (Box 23, Media ID: 231.0367)
      1. News Notes: The aftermath of the RNC is covered, as well as openly-gay candidates running for election in the city. Christopher Lynn's campaign is covered, and Lynn is interviewed by Andy Humm. Richard Irizarry is interviewed.
      COMMERCIAL: Icelandair
      2. Report from the Capitol: Tim McFeely is interviewed about the lack of sufficient funding for AIDS recovery. AIDS Watch '92 will address this.
      3. Sports Extra: Gutter George and Bill Baumer cover bowling.
      4. Interview with Blanche Wiesen Cook, author of Eleanor Roosevelt Volume 1. Eleanor Roosevelt's impact on the modern gay and lesbian movement is covered.
      5. Jim Hubbard announces the Lesbian and Gay Experimental Film Festival. Clips from the films, including "Holy Mary" and "Dyke After Dyke" are shown.
      6. Naming Names: Newsweek runs a cover story on violence against gays, which covers the right wing's 'homosexual agenda' propaganda. Viewers are encouraged to write to Newsweek, and Richard Smith, editor-in-chief.
      7. The Roving Camera: John Calendo on Fire Island covering a fundraiser.
      8. Lavender Health: Yvette Burton, director of Lesbian and Gay Health Initiative is interviewed.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 38 [Air date: 9/17/1992], September 1992; ID: 231.0368 (Box 23, Media ID: 231.0368)
      1. News Notes: The passing of Ted Weiss. George Will asks if homosexuality is a choice or an affliction. The AIDS education initiative is dismantled in New York City. Anthony Perkins and Mel Rosen's deaths are covered. Dan Quayle makes out-of-touch statements.
      2. GCN attends a press conference. A group of forty people assaulted two gay men in Chelsea. Ruth Messinger speaks and endorses hate crime legislation, and is trying to get all forty people charged. Tom Duane speaks about shutting down clubs such as The Home Base. Andrew Stein and Dennis De Leon speak.
      3. Lou Maletta reports on a letter from the Vatican, in which the Vatican states it will continue to discriminate against gays and lesbians. Dignity New York is fighting back. Joe Raimondi and Christine Nusse are interviewed. Information on Dignity's conference for Catholic Lesbians is shown.
      4. Marilyn Quayle is met with hundreds of protesters in Maine, and her speech is disrupted. Footage is shown.
      5. Andy Humm at the B Dalton Book Shop in Greenwich Village. Joseph Steffan has written a book about being kicked out of the Navy two weeks before graduation because he was gay. Sandra Lowe is also interviewed.
      6. Report From the Capitol: Lavender Republicans For Clinton is covered. Susan Jester is interviewed.
      7. The Roving Camera: John Calendo at Wigstock '92. Perfidia, Deborah Harry, Michael Musto, Robert Sherman, and others are interviewed.
      8. GCN Sports: Bodybuilding competitions and softball are covered.
      9. Lavender Health: Marjorie Hill is interviewed about education in New York.
      10. Naming Names: Officer Mitch Grobeson comes out and is faced with death threats. A 60 Minutes segment covers his case. Viewers are encouraged to write to Don Hewitt, executive producer of 60 Minutes.
      11. Primary Update: Ted Weiss is posthumously re-elected to his seat.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 39 [Air date: 9/24/1992], September 1992; ID: 231.0369 (Box 24, Media ID: 231.0369)
      1. News Notes: Helms amendments are passed. Humm talks about the memorial service for his dentist, Russell Aaron. Donald Grasso, part of the No on 9 Committee, which is trying to block anti-gay laws from being passed in Oregon is interviewed. The address for the No on 9 Committee is displayed.
      2. ACT UP protests George Bush's visit to New York. Police are seen arresting a few protesters.
      3. Letter from Vatican causes stir. Joe Raimondi of Dignity New York is interviewed during a protest outside a cathedral.
      4. At the Lesbian and Gay Community Center, Luis Reyas of the NYC Board of Education is interviewed during a town meeting on attacks on gay-positive education, the Children of the Rainbow. Bronx District 12, Queens District 24, Staten Island District 31, and Brooklyn Districts 21 and 22 are opposing the material. Frances Krunreuther of the Hetrick-Martin Institute is also interviewed. Viewers are encouraged to counter the homophobia of the Board of Education by attending a meeting.
      5. Report From The Capitol: Gregory King in Columbus, Ohio. Steven Schellabarger, Lynn Greer, Phyllis Gorman, and Tim McCarthy are interviewed about a gay positive campaign commercial. This segment has very distorted audio.
      6. David N. visits a synagogue for gay and lesbian Jews, the Beth Simchat Torah. Rabbi Sharon Kliembaum is interviewed.
      7. Lambda Book Review: Several publications run stories on the 'mainstreaming of gay literature'. Deacon MacCubin, owner of Lambda Rising Books is interviewed. Anne Rice and Mercedes Lackey are mentioned. Man on the street interviews are conducted in which participants are asked about gay literature.
      8. Naming Names: Charlie Rose features Joseph Steffan, who was discharged from the military for being gay. Viewers are encouraged to write to WNET.
      9. Lavender Health: Guillermo Vasques of the Gay Men's Health Crisis is interviewed.
      10. The passing of Bob Caviano is announced.
      11. A clip from the Republican convention is shown in which Phyllis Schlafly is asked about what she would do if one of her children turned out to be gay. One of her children turned out to be gay.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 40 [Air date: 10/1/1992], October 1992; ID: 231.0370 (Box 24, Media ID: 231.0370)
      1. News Notes: National Coming Out Day. An article is run, 'Is Dan Quayle a Homosexual?' Andy Humm talks about how he had interviewed Quayle's gay lover in 1988. Jerry Nadler doesn't know what a red ribbon means.
      2. Liz Crisonio, who was discriminated against and fired by Department of General Services' Art Simes is interviewed. Crisonio taped Simes' homophobic comments, and went to the Human Rights Commission. Humm states that GCN is trying to contact Simes.
      COMMERCIAL: 970-BIG-1 (new)
      3. DIFFA gets donation of 500 laserdisc players and discs dealing with the AIDS virus from electronics company Pioneer. Mr. Matsumoto, Jeanne White, Hank Evers, Susan Sarandon,. The laserdisc is meant to educate people on AIDS and HIV; a few excerpts are shown, including Ted Koppel introducing the disc.
      4. Lee Sharmat gets an exclusive interview with Leanza Cornett, the new Miss America, who has stated she is going to push AIDS activism.
      5. Report from the Capitol: Tacie Dejanikus, deputy field director of the Human Rights Campaign Fund is interviewed about Field Operation.
      6. Gods Love We Deliver: Frank Abdale, deputy executive director of the organization introduces a healthy cooking segment hosted by Steven Welch. Ronald Grossman and Vivica Kraak, two MDs are interviewed, as is Dan Bloom, a critic social worker.
      COMMERCIAL: McKay Drugs
      7. Naming Names: Gay and lesbian weddings get news in the Austin-American Statesman, then national news coverage. Viewers are encouraged to write to Phil Donahue's show, which gave positive portrayal of the weddings.
      8. Lavender Health: Margaret Hamburg, commissioner of health, is interviewed.
      COMMERCIAL: Manhattan Center for Living
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 41 [Air date: 10/8/1992], October 1992; ID: 231.0371 (Box 24, Media ID: 231.0371)
      1. News Notes: Sinead O'Connor ripping up the picture of the pope on SNL is covered. Barbara Bush says 'sex equals death' on Larry King. The Oregon anti-gay laws are struck down.
      2. A massive anti-gay demonstration takes place at the Board of Education, Lee Sharmat interviews the anti-gay protesters. Steven Di Brienza is interviewed. Counter-protesters are interviewed as well.
      3. Empire State Pride Agenda's First Annual Awards Dinner and The 25th Anniversary of The Advocate: Gay Men's Health Crisis, Sandra Jay Lowe, and New York State Abortion Rights Action League are honored. Dick Dadey and Rodger McFarlane are interviewed. Jeff Yarbrough, editor of the Advocate is interviewed about the magazine's history.
      4. Report From the Capitol: Gregory King interviews Paul Cooper, the project manager for HRCF is interviewed about Bill Clinton.
      5. Astrea Foundation gives awards. A reading by Melinda Goodman is shown. Katherine Acey, executive director, is interviewed.
      6. GCN Sports: Two new co-presidents are sworn in for Gay Games IV. Columbus Day Weekend sees Challenge '92, the gay and lesbian soccer tournament.
      7. Naming Names: Banana Republic's gay-positive ad campaign is covered. Viewers are encouraged to write to Banana Republic.
      8. Lavender Health: Mark Barnes is interviewed.
      COMMERCIAL: Register to Vote – Lou Maletta voiceover
      9. Andy Humm mentions ACT UP is going to try and dump ashes of AIDS victims on the White House lawn. The music video for Madonna's Vogue plays after the credits.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 42 [Air date: 10/15/1992], October 1992; ID: 231.0372 (Box 24, Media ID: 231.0372)
      231 0372
      1. News Notes: Humm and Sharmat discuss the presidential debate. Viewers are encouraged to donate to campaigns in Oregon and Colorado to fight anti-gay legislation. George Bush mentions ACT UP. The New York Times Magazine runs story 'Gay Politics Goes Mainstream'.
      2. The AIDS quilt is shown in Washington, DC. A candle light vigil in DC is also shown. Political Funeral (Ashes Action) by ACT UP is shown. Multiple ACT UP protesters dumps ashes on the White House lawn. Hands Around the White House, protesters chant "Three more weeks you're out!" A title appears on screen 'Silence = Death. Vote!'
      3. Dr. Mervyn F. Silverman introduces ads by AmFAR (American Federation for AIDS Research). Several of the ads are shown, and feature Elizabeth Taylor. Rev. Margaret Reinfeld, director of education, talks about the ads.
      4. The play Murder in Disguise is covered. John Glines, the writer is interviewed. Excerpts from the play are shown.
      5. Report from the Capitol: Tim McFeely is interviewed about the HRCF's actions during the election.
      6. Lee Sharmat interviews Alain Montour of Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays.
      7. Naming Names: A homophobic Republican campaign ad is covered, which the Christian Action Network funded. Viewers are encouraged to write to Tom Bettag, executive producer of Nightline.
      COMMERCIAL: Stop the Bullshit. Get Out and Vote!
      8. Lavender Health: Ellen Zaltsberg covers the Children of the Rainbow controversy. An anti-gay protest in Brooklyn, targeting the Children of the Rainbow curriculum is covered and footage is shown. Myra Iramon of WHAM, Dr. Luis O. Reyes, Katherine Acey of the Astraea Foundation, Marjorie Hill, Andy Montoya, a gay high school student, Doug Robinson of Center Kids, Katherine Kennedy, are interviewed during the counter-protest.
      9. Footage from the DC candlelight vigil are shown over the end credits.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 43 [Air date: 10/22/1992], October 1992; ID: 231.0373 (Box 24, Media ID: 231.0373)
      1. News Notes: Murders in Oregon over Ballot Measure 9. Brian H Moch had his house firebombed and was killed, and a lesbian named Hattie Mae Cohens. The Cracker Barrel controversy is covered. A clip from Andy Humm interviewing Alfonse D'Amato in 1988 at the Republican National Convention. D'Amato's anti-gay rights voting record is covered. Reactions to the debate are shown; no names of the interviewees are shown.
      2. Pete Wilson finally passes a gay and lesbian rights bill. Footage from a demonstration in California is shown; it is unclear when this footage is from. Phil Wilson and Dolly Gei speak.
      3. Report from the Capitol: Eric Rosenthal, political director of HRCF is interviewed about the election.
      COMMERCIAL: Parents and Friends of Lesbian and Gays Dinner and Dance at the Roosevelt Hotel
      4. Yale Alexander interviews Everett Quinton, the director and star of the play Brother Truckers. An excerpt from the play is shown
      COMMERCIAL: Brother Truckers
      5. Lou Maletta interviews Marvin Liebman, the author of Coming Out Conservative.
      COMMERCIAL: Women's Candlelight March in Support of Clinton and Gore
      6. Nick Curto and Val Coleman of The Stonewall Business Association are interviewed.
      COMMERCIAL: The Plot, a play
      7. Naming Names: WBLS plays Buju Banton's "Boom Bye Bye", which encourages listeners to shoot gay men. Viewers are encouraged to write to WBLS to pull the song and run PSAs.
      8. Lavender Health: Ronald Johnson is interviewed. In the middle of the interview, the video suddenly cuts into an interview with Larry Pagnoti of the Upper Room AIDS Ministry. The address of the Upper Room AIDS Ministry is displayed.
      COMMERCIAL: The Pleasure Chest COMMERCIAL: Murder in Disguise, a play
      9. Humm and Sharmat encourage viewers to vote, and the No On 9 campaign is mentioned again, with viewers encouraged to donate.
      COMMERCIAL: Take Back the Night
      10. A clip from the Democratic National Convention speech by Bill Clinton is shown.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 44 [Air date: 10/29/1992], October 1992; ID: 231.0374 (Box 24, Media ID: 231.0374)
      1. News Notes: The New York Times covers an AIDS treatment vaccine controversy, in which a single company got $20 million for research. WBLS apologizes for playing "Boom Bye Bye".
      2. ACT UP protests Al D'Amoto. Protesting outside D'Amoto's headquarters. A protester says they were dragged out of D'Amoto's office.
      3. Andy Humm talks briefly about the Domestic Partnership Bill. A hearing is being held on two 'piecemeal' bills at City Hall. Christopher Lynn and Tom Duane are interviewed.
      4. Lawyers Susan Camp-Stocks and Merril Hirsch are interviewed about suing the Boy Scouts of America in Washington DC. Roland Poole and Michael Geller are mentioned.
      5. Lee Sharmat interviews Margaret Kammenmyer, who was kicked out of the military because of her sexual orientation.
      6. Bill Mitchell and Dana Greene of the Community Health Project are interviewed. A Celebration of Family Values is announced, taking place at the Copa on 60th Street. Philip Stoehr is interviewed.
      COMMERCIAL: A Celebration of Family Values
      7. Lou Maletta encourages viewers to vote. David Strah and Valerie Gamache have set up Vote and Dance, a celebration.
      8. Women's Candlelight March in Support of Clinton and Gore. Lee Sharmat interviews several participants.
      9. Naming Names: A 20/20 focus piece on North Hampton, MA is celebrated. Viewers are encouraged to write to executive producer Victor Neufeld.
      10. Lavender Health: Part two of Ronald Johnson interview. A visit to the PWA Coalition on west 26th street for an interview with Chris Babick.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 45 [Air date: 11/5/1992], November 1992; ID: 231.0375 (Box 24, Media ID: 231.0375)
      1. News Notes: Post election. Oregon's prop 9 is struck down, but it still receives 45% of the vote; Colorado's anti-gay legislation passes. Barney Frank is re-elected. Al D'Amoto gets elected.
      2. The Empire State Pride Agenda's Election Night Party at the Roxy. Lee Sharmat interviews several attendees. Marjorie Hill and Dick Dadey are interviewed. A bumper is shown 'Congratulations Bill Clinton From Gay USA'.
      3. ACT UP carries the body of Mark Lowe Fisher through the streets of New York to show George Bush's neglect of AIDS victims. Protesters carry a huge banner reading 'MARK LOWE FISHER. 1953-1992. DIED OF AIDS. MURDERED BY GEORGE BUSH.' The coffin is deposited at the Republican Headquarters of New York on 43rd Street, the day before Election Day.
      4. The Roving Camera: National Coming Out Day. A clip from 'The Wizard of Oz' is shown. Men and women who have come out are interviewed. Scenes from the Gay and Lesbian Community Center on Coming Out Day are shown.
      5. Naming Names: Josh Machleder reports on Melrose Place addressing gay bashing and homophobia. The series Key West is being protested by Focus on the Family. Viewers are encouraged to write to Peter Chernin, president of Fox.
    - Gay USA, Vol. X, Episode No. 46 [Air date: 11/12/1992], November 1992; ID: 231.0376 (Box 24, Media ID: 231.0376)
      1. News Notes: Magic Johnson leaving the NBA is covered.
      2. Ed Anderson at the Century Plaza Hotel for an anniversary celebration of the Los Angeles Gay and Lesbian Services Center. Torie Osborn are interviewed. Lou Maletta, before the segment, states the quality is not up to their standards; it appears to be sourced from a VHS tape.
      3. Lambda Report: Colorado bans gay rights laws. Speeches by Cathy Reynolds, Tony Ogden, Roy Romer are shown. A protest against Amendment 2 from later on in election night is shown. Roy Romer's speech the following morning is shown. Pat Schroeder also speaks.
      4. The footage of Beth Liebo being arrested by police at the Republican National Convention is shown. Beth Liebo is then interviewed about being given trumped-up charges of assault of a police officer (later dropped to a class D misdemeanor) and arranging a trial-by-jury lawsuit of the Texas police.
      5. The Roosevelt Hotel hosts the Parents of Lesbian and Gays annual banquet. David Dinkins speaks. Jean Manfort, founder of P-FLAG is interviewed. Ruth Messinger speaks.
      6. Naming Names: Roseanne adds a lesbian character, Nancy. Its noted that Nancy is the only recurring lesbian character in a primetime show. Viewers are encouraged to write to Carsey Werner Company, the producers of the show.
      7. David Harris of the Arkansas Gay and Lesbian Task Force is interviewed.
      8. Lavender Health: Daisy De Jesus, Cynthia Acevedo, and Linda Gang are interviewed about being 'butch'.
      9. Report from the Capitol: Kay Ostberg, program director at the Human Rights Campaign Fund is interviewed.